This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
This is Jeremy Jung for Software
Engineering Radio, and today I'm talking
to Paul Frazee. He's the current CTO of
Blue Sky, and he previously worked on
other decentralized applications like
Beaker and Secure Scuttlebutt. Paul,
welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks for having me.
For people who aren't familiar with Blue
Sky, what is it?
So, Blue Sky is an open social network.
Simple as way to put it. Designed in
particular for high scale. That's kind
of one of the big requirements that we
had when we were moving into it. And it
is really geared towards making sure
that the operation of the social network
is open amongst multiple different
organizations. So, we're one of the
operators, but other folks can come in,
spin up the software, all the open
source software, and essentially have a
full node with a full copy of the
network, active users, and have their
users join into our network, and they
all work functionally as one shared
application.
So, it sounds like it's similar to say
Twitter, but instead of there just being
one Twitter, there could be any number,
and there is part of the underlying
protocol that allows them to all connect
to one another and act as one system.
That's exactly right. And there's a
metaphor we use a lot, which is compared
to the web and search engines, which
actually kind of matches really well.
Like when you use Bing or Google, you're
searching the same web. So, on the app
protocol on Blue Sky, you use Blue Sky,
you use some alternative client or
application, all the same. We call it
the atmosphere, all one shared network.
And more than just the the client, cuz I
think sometimes when people think of a
client, they'll think of I use a web
browser, I could use Chrome or Firefox,
but ultimately I'm connecting to the
same thing. But, it's not just people
running alternate clients, right? It's
also running their own social networks
in a way.
Their own full back end to it. That's
right. Yeah. The agreeing point on that
being the firehose of data that runs the
entire thing is open as well. And so,
you start up your own application, you
spin up a service that's just pipes into
that firehose and taps into all all the
activity.
And so, talking about this underlying
protocol, maybe we could start where
this all began so people get some
context for where this all came from.
All right. So, let's wind the clock back
here in my brain. We started out 2022
right at the beginning of the year. We
were formed as a essentially a
consulting company outside of Twitter
with a contract with Twitter. And our
goal was to build a protocol that could
have run Twitter much like the way that
we just described, which set us up with
a couple of pretty specific
requirements. For one, we had to make
sure that it could scale. So, that ended
up being a really important first
requirement. And we wanted to make sure
that there was strong kind of guarantees
that the network doesn't ever get
captured by anyone operator. So, the
idea was that Twitter would become the
first adopter of the technology. Other
applications, other services would begin
to take advantage of it and users would
be able to smoothly migrate their
accounts in between one or the other at
any time. And it's really anchored in a
particular goal of just deconstructing
monopolies, getting rid of those modes
that make it so that there's a kind of a
lack of competition between these
things, and making sure that if there
was some kind of reason that you decided
you're just not happy with what
direction this service has been going,
you move over to another one, you're
still in touch with all the folks you
were in touch with before, you don't
lose your data, you don't lose your
followers. Those were the kind of
initial requirements that we set out
with. The team, by and large, came from
the decentralized web movement, which is
actually a pretty large community that's
been around since, I want to say, around
2012 is when we first kind of started to
form. It got really made more
specifically into a community somewhere
around 2015 or 16, I want to say, when
the Internet Archive started to host
conferences for us, and so that gave us
kind of a meeting point where we all
started to meet up. There's kind of
three schools of thought within that
movement. There was the blockchain
community, the federation community, and
the peer-to-peer community. And so,
blockchain, you you know, don't need to
explain that one. You got federation,
which was largely ActivityPub, Mastodon.
And then peer-to-peer was IPFS, that
protocol, Secure Scuttlebutt, those
kinds of, you know, BitTorrent-style
technologies, really. They're all kind
of inspired by that. So, these three
different kind of subcommunities were
all working independently on different
ways to attack how to make these open
applications. You know, how do you get
something that's a high-scale web
application without one corporation
being the only operator? When this team
came together in 2022, we largely
sourced from the peer-to-peer group of
the decentralized community. Personally,
I'd been working in the space and on
those kinds of technologies for about 10
years at that stage, and the other folks
that were in there, five to 10 each,
respectively. So, we all had had a fair
amount of time working on that, and we
had really kind of hit some of the
limitations of doing things entirely
using client devices. We were running
into challenges about reliability of
connections, you know, punching holes
through the individual devices very
hard, synchronizing keys between the
devices very hard, maintaining strong
availability of the data because
people's devices are going off and on,
things like that. Even when you're using
the kind of BitTorrent style of shared
distribution, that becomes a challenge.
But, probably the worst challenge was,
uh surprisingly, scale. You need to be
able to create aggregations of a lot of
behavior, even when you're trying to
model your application as largely
peer-wise interactions, like the thing I
like messaging. You might be an
aggregation of like accounts that even
exist. How do you do notifications
reliably, things like that? Really
challenging. And what I was starting to
say to myself by the end of that kind of
peer-to-peer setup was that it just it
can't be rocket science to do a comment
section, you know? Like, at some point
you just ask yourself, like, how hard
are we willing to work to to make these
ideas work? But, there were some pretty
good pieces of tech that did come out of
the peer-to-peer world. A lot of it had
to do with what I might call
cryptographic structure. Things like
Merkle trees, you know, and advances
within Merkle trees. Ways to take data
sets and reduce them down to hashes, so
that you can then create my signatures
and have signed data sets at rest at
larger scales. So, our basic thought
was, well, all right. We got some pretty
good tech out of this, but let's drop
that requirement that it all run off of
devices and let's take it to some
servers in there.
And instead, almost kind of think of the
entire network as a peer-to-peer mesh of
servers. That's going to solve your
scale problem, because you can throw up
big databases at it. It's going to solve
your availability problems. It's going
to solve your device sync problems. But,
you get a lot of the same properties of
being able to move data sets between
services, much like you could move them
between devices in the peer-to-peer
network, without losing their
identifiers, because you're doing this
in direction of cryptographic
identifiers to the current host. That's
what peer-to-peer always is always
doing. You're taking like a public key
or hash, and then you're asking the
network, "Hey, who has this?" Well, if
you just move that into the server, you
get the same thing. That dynamic
resolution of who's your active host.
So, you're getting that portability that
we wanted real bad. And then you're also
getting that kind of in-meshing of the
different services, where each of them
is producing these data sets that they
can sync from each other. So, take
peer-to-peer and apply it to the server
stack and that was our kind of initial
thought of like, hey, you know what?
This might work. This might solve the
problems that we have. And a lot of the
design fell out from that basic
mentality.
When you talk about these cryptographic
identifiers, is the idea that anybody
could have data about a person, like a
message or a comment, and that could be
hosted different places, but you would
still know which person that originally
came from? Is that the goal there?
That's exactly it. Yeah, you want to
create identification
that supersedes servers, right? So, when
you think about like, if I'm using
Twitter
and I want to know what your posts are,
I go to twitter.com/jeremy,
right? I'm asking Twitter and your ID is
consequently always bound to Twitter.
You're always kind of a second-class
identifier. We wanted to boost up the
user identifier to be kind of
a thing free standing on its own. I want
to just know what Jeremy's posts are.
And then, once you get into the
technical system, it'll be designed to
figure out, okay, who knows that? Who
can answer that for you? We use
cryptographic identifiers internally.
So, like all the data sets use these
kind of long URLs to identify things.
But in the the live system, we ended up
using uh like in the application, the
user-facing part, we use domain names
for people, which kind of I think gives
the picture of how this all operates. It
really moves the user accounts up into a
free standing first-class identifier
within the system. And then,
consequently, whatever application
you're using, it's really about whatever
data is getting put into your account
and then that just exchanges between any
application anybody else is using.
So, in this case, it sounds like the
identifier is some long string that not
sure if it's necessarily human readable
or not. You're shaking your head no.
Shaking your head no.
But if you have that string, you know
it's for a specific person, and since
it's not really human-readable, what you
do is you put a layer on top of it,
which is in this case is a domain that
somebody can use to look up and find the
identifier.
Yeah. Yeah, so we just use DNS. You put
a TXT record in there, map it to that
long string, or you can do a dot
well-known file on a web server if
that's more convenient for you. And then
the ID that's behind that, the
non-human-readable one, those are called
DIDs, which is actually a W3C spec.
Those then map to a kind of a
certificate, uh what do you call it, DID
document, that kind of confirms the
binding by declaring what the that
domain name should be. So, you get this
bidirectional binding. And then that
certificate also includes signing keys
and active servers. So, you pull down
that certificate, and that's how the
discovery of the active server happens
is through the DID system.
So, when you refer to an active server,
what is that server, and what is that
server storing?
It's kind of like a web server, but
instead of hosting HTML, it's hosting
The simplest way to put it is like a
bunch of JSON records. Every user has
their own kind of document store of JSON
documents that's bucketed into
collections.
Whenever you're looking up somebody on
the network, you're going to get an
access to that repository of data, jump
into a collection, and this collection
is their post collection.
Get the RT, and then you pull out JSON
at the end of it, which is just a
structured piece of stuff saying,
"Here's the created at, here's the text,
here's the type," things like that. It's
really kind of one way you could look at
the whole system is as a giant giant
database network.
So, if someone's going to look up
someone's identifier, let's say they
have the
user's domain, they have to go to some
source, right, to find
Right.
the user's data. You've mentioned, I
think before, the idea that this is
decentralized, and by default, I would
picture some kind of centralized
resource where I send somebody a domain,
and then they give me back the
identifier and the links to the servers.
So, how does that work in practice where
it actually can be decentralized?
Yeah, I mean, the servers are pretty
dumb, right? They're just hosting those
data repositories for you. So, what
you're doing is I mentioned that your
DID, that non-human readable identifier,
and that has that certificate attached
to it that lists servers and signing
keys and things like that. So, you're
just going to look up inside that DID
document what that server is, your data
repository host. And then you contact
that guy and say, "All right, I'm told
that you're hosting this thing. You
know, here's the person I'm looking for.
Hand over the data." So, it's really,
you know, pretty straightforward. The
way that gets decentralized is by dint
of the fact that I could swap out that
active server that's in my certificate,
you know? And probably when I rotate the
signing keys cuz I've just changed the,
you know, I don't want to keep using the
same signing keys as I was using
previously cuz I just changed to the
authority. So, that's the migration.
Change the hosting server, change out
the signing keys. Somebody that's
looking for me now, they're going to
load up my document, my DID document.
They're going to say, "Okay. Oh, new
server, new keys. Pull down the data.
Looks good, right? Matches up with the
DID doc. So, that's how you get that
level of portability, but when those
changes happen, the DID doesn't change,
right? The DID document changes. So,
there's a level of indirection there.
And that's pretty important because if
you don't have a persistent identifier,
whenever you're trying to change out
servers, all those backlinks are going
to break. That's the kind of stuff that
stops you from being able to do clean
migrations on things like web-based
services. The only real option is to go
out and ask everybody to update their
data. And when you're talking about like
interactions in a social network, like
people replying to each other, there's
no chance, right? You know, every time
somebody moves, you're going to go back
and modify all those records. You don't
even control all the records from the
top down cuz they're hosted all over the
web. So, this is you can't do it. So,
generally we call this account
portability that you're kind of like
phone number portability that you can
change your host, but so that part's
portable, but the ID stays the same. And
that's keeping that ID the same is the
real key to make it sure that this can
happen without breaking the whole
system.
And so it sounds like there's the
decentralized ID, then there's the
decentralized ID document that's
associated with that that points you to
where the actual location of your data,
your posts, your pictures, and whatnot.
But then you also mentioned that they
could change servers, I guess. So, let's
say somebody changes where their data is
stored, that would change the servers, I
guess, in their document. But then how
do all of these systems know, okay, I
need to change all these references to
your old server to these new servers?
Yeah. Well, the good news is that you
only have to You got the public data set
of all the users' activity, and then you
have like internal caches of where the
current server is. You just got to
update those internal caches when you're
trying to contact their server. So, it's
actually a pretty minimal thing to just
like update like, "Oh, they moved." Just
start talking to the update my table, my
Redis that's holding on to that kind of
temporary information, put it on TTL,
that sort of thing. And honestly, in
practice, a fair amount of the system,
for scalability reasons, doesn't
necessarily work by servers directly
contacting each other. It's actually a
little bit more like how I told you
before, I'm going to use this metaphor a
lot, the search engines with the web,
right?
What we do is we actually end up
crawling the repositories that are out
in the world and following them into
event streams, like a Kafka. And that
allows the entire system to act like a
data processing pipeline, where you're
just tapping into these event streams,
and then pushing those logs into
databases that produce like these
large-scale aggregations. So, a lot of
the application behavior ends up working
off of these event logs. If I reply to
somebody, for instance, I don't
necessarily It's not my server has to
like talk to your server and say, "Hey,
I'm replying to you." What I do is I
just publish a reply in my repository,
that gets shot out into the event logs,
and then these aggregators pick up that
the reply got created and just update
their database with it. So, it's not
that our hosting servers are constantly
having to send messages with each other.
You actually use these aggregators to
pull together the picture of what's
happening on the network.
Okay, so like you were saying, it's an
event stream model where everybody
publishes the events the things that
they're doing, whether that's making a
new post, making a reply, that's all
being posted to this event stream, and
then everybody who provides, I'm not
sure if instance is the right term, but
an implementation of the atmosphere
protocol,
they are listening for all those
changes, and they don't necessarily
have to know that you moved servers
because they're just listening for the
events.
And you still have the same identifier.
Generally speaking, yeah, cuz like if
you're listening to one of these event
streams, what you end up looking for is
just the signature on it and making sure
that the signature matches up because
you're not actually having to talk to
their live server, you're just listening
to this relay that's doing this
aggregation for you.
But I think actually to kind of give a
little more clarity to what you're
talking about, it might be a good idea
to kind of refocus how we're talking
about the system here. I mentioned
before that our goal was to make a
high-scale system, right? We need to
handle a lot of data. And if you're
thinking about this in the way that
Mastodon does it or the ActivityPub
model, that's actually going to give you
the wrong intuition cuz we chose a
dramatically different system. What we
did instead was we picked up essentially
the same practices you're going to use
for a data center, a high-scale
application data center. Instead, all
right, how do you tend to build these
sorts of things? Well, what you're going
to do is you're going to have multiple
different services running different
purposes. It gets pretty close to a
microservices approach. You're going to
have a set of databases, and then you're
going to generally speaking for high
scale you're going to have an event some
kind of a Kafka some kind of a event log
that you are tossing changes about the
state of these databases into and then
you have a bunch of secondary systems
that are tapping into the event log and
processing that into the large scale
databases like your search index your
nice post grades of user profiles and
that makes sure that you can you get
each of these different systems to
perform really well at their particular
task and then you can detach them in
their design. For instance, your primary
storage can be just a key value store
that scales horizontally and then on the
event log you're using a Kafka that's
designed to handle particular semantics
of making sure that the messages don't
get dropped that they come through at a
particular throughput and then you're
using for us we're using like ScyllaDB
for the big scale indexes that scales
horizontally really well so it's just
different kind of profiles for different
pieces. If you read Kleppmann's book
data intensive applications I think it's
called a lot of it gets captured there.
He talks a lot about this kind of thing
it's sometimes called a Kappa
architecture is one way this is
described event sourcing is a similar
term for it as well stream processing.
That's pretty standard practices for how
you would build a traditional high scale
service. So if you take this this kind
of microservice architecture and
essentially say okay now imagine that
each of the services that are part of
your data center could be hosted by
anybody not just within our data center
but outside of our data center as well
and should be able to all work together.
That's basically how the App Proto is
designed. So we were talking about the
data repository host those are just the
primary data stores. They hold on to the
user keys and they hold on to those JSON
records and then we have another service
category we call relay that just crawls
those data repositories and sucks in
that fire hose of data we were talking
about that event log and then we have
what we call App Views that sit there
and tail the log and produce indexes off
of it. They're listening to those events
and then like making threads, you know,
like okay, that guy posted, that guy
replied, that guy replied, that's a
thread. They assemble it into that form.
So, when you're running an application,
you're talking to the app view to read
the network and you're talking to the
hosts to write to network. And each of
these different pieces sync up together
in this open mesh. So, we really took a
traditional sort of data center model
and just turned it inside out where each
piece is a part of the protocol and
communicated with each other and
therefore anybody can join into that
mesh.
And to
just make sure I am tracking, the data
repository is the data about the user.
So, it has your
decentralized identifier, it has your
replies, your posts, all that sort of
thing. And then you have a relay which
its responsibility is to somehow find
all of those data repositories and
collect them as they happen so that it
can publish them to some kind of event
stream. And then you have the app view
which it's receiving messages from the
relay as they happen and then it can
have its own store and index that for
search, it can collect them in a way so
that it can present them onto a UI, that
sort of thing. That's the user-facing
part, I suppose.
Yeah, that's exactly it. And again, it's
it's actually quite similar to how the
web works if you combine together the
relay and app view. You know, the web
works where you got all these different
websites, they're hosting their stuff
and then the search engine is going
around aggregating all that data and
turning it into a search experience.
Totally the same model. It's just being
applied to more varieties of data, like
structured data, like posts and replies,
follows, likes, all that kind of stuff.
And then instead of producing a search
application at the end,
I mean, it does that, too, but it also
produces, you know, timelines and
threads and people's profiles and stuff
like that. So, it's actually pretty spog
standard way of doing, you know, like
that's one of the models that we've seen
work for large-scale decentralized
systems. And so, we're just transposing
it onto something that kind of is more
focused towards social applications.
So, I think I'm tracking that the data
repository itself, since it has your
decentralized identifier and because the
data is cryptographically signed, you
know, it's from a specific user. I think
the part that I'm still not quite sure
about is the relays. I understand if you
run all the data repositories, you know
where they are, so you know how to
collect the data from them. But, if
someone's running another system outside
of your organization, how do they find
your data repositories or do they have
to connect to your relay? What's the
intention for that?
That logic runs again really similar to
how search engines find out about
websites. So, there is actually a way
for one of these data hosts to contact
relay and say, "Hey, I exist, you know,
go ahead and get my stuff." And then
it'll be up to the relay to decide like
if they want it or not. Right now,
generally, we're just like, "Yeah, you
know, we we want it, you know." But, as
you can imagine, as the thing matures
and gets to higher scale, there might be
some trust kind of things to worry
about, you know. That's kind of the
naive operation that currently exists,
but over time, as the network gets
bigger and bigger, it'll probably
involve some more traditional kind of
spidering behaviors. Because, you know,
as more relays come into the system,
each of these hosts, they're not going
to know who to talk to. You're trying to
start a new relay. What they're going to
do is they're going to discover all of
the different users that exist in the
system by, you know, looking at what
data they have to start with, you know.
Probably involve a little bit of a
manual feeding in at first, whenever I'm
starting up a relay, like, "Okay,
there's Blue Sky's relay. Let me just
pull what they know." And then I go from
there. And then anytime you discover a
new user you don't have, like, "Oh, I'll
look them up. Pull them into the relay,
too." right? So, there's a pretty
straightforward discovery process that
you'll just have to bake into a relay to
make sure you're calling as much of the
network as possible.
And so, I don't think we've defined the
term federation, but maybe you could
explain what that is and if that is what
this is.
We are so unsure.
Okay.
Yeah, this just jams us up pretty bad
because I think everybody can Everybody
just pretty strongly agrees that
ActivityPub is federation, right? And
ActivityPub kind of models itself pretty
similarly to email in a way. Like, the
metaphors they use is that there's
inboxes and outboxes, and every
ActivityPub server, they're setting up
the full vertical stack. They set up the
primary hosting, the views of the data
that's happening there, the interface
for the application, all of it pretty
traditional like closed service, but
then they're kind of using the
perimeter, they're making that permeable
by sending exchanging essentially
mailing records to each other, right?
That's their kind of logic of how that
works. And that's pretty much in line
with I think what most people think of
with federation. Whereas, what we're
doing isn't like that. We've cut Instead
of having a bunch of vertical stacks
communicating horizontally with each
other, we kind of sliced in the other
direction. We sliced horizontally into
this microservices mesh and have like a
total mix and match of different
microservices between different
operators. Is that federation? I don't
know, right? We tried to invent a term,
didn't really work.
You know, at the moment we just kind of
don't worry about it that much, see what
happens, see what the world sort of has
to say to us about it. But, I compare it
to the web a lot because it shares a lot
of properties with how the web works,
the web and kind of search engine
dynamic. And beyond that, yeah, I don't
know.
Cuz I'm trying to picture the
distinction here. So, with
I think people probably are thinking of
something like say a Mastodon instance
Mhm.
when you're talking about everything
being included. The webpage where you
view the Postgres database that's
keeping the messages and that same
instance, it's responsible for basically
everything.
Mhm.
And I believe what you're saying is that
the difference with the authenticated
transfer protocol is that the Okay.
AT protocol, yep.
And the difference there is that at the
protocol level you split it up into the
data itself, which can be validated
completely separately from other parts
of the system. Like you could have the
JSON files on your hard drive and
somebody else can have that same JSON
file and they would know who the user is
and that these are real things that user
posted. That's like a separate part and
then the relay component that looks for
all these different repositories that
has people's data. That can also be its
own independent thing where its job is
just to output events and that can exist
just by itself. It doesn't need the
application part, the the user-facing
part. It can just be this event stream
on itself. And that's the part where it
sounds like you can make decisions on
who to collect data from. I guess you
have to agree that somebody can connect
to you and get the users from your data
repositories and likewise other people
that run relays, they also have to agree
to let you pull the users from theirs.
Yeah, that's right. Yeah.
And so I think the Mastodon example
makes sense, but I wonder if the
underlying ActivityPub protocol forces
you to use it in that way in like a
whole full application that talks to
another full application or is it more
like that's just how people tend to use
it and it's not necessarily a
characteristic of the protocol.
Yeah, it's a good question actually. So,
you know, generally what I would say is
pretty core to the protocol is the
expectations about how the services
interact with each other. So, the
mailbox metaphor that's used in the
ActivityPub. So, in that design, if I
reply to you, I'll update my local
database with what I did and then I'll
send a message over to your server
saying, "Hey, by the way, add this
reply. I did this." And that's how they
find out about things. That's how they
find out about activity outside of their
network. That's the part that as long as
you're doing ActivityPub, I suspect
you're going to see reliably happening.
I can say for sure that's a pretty tight
requirement that's ActivityPub. If you
wanted to split it up the way we're
talking about, you could.
I don't know if you necessarily would
want to because I don't know. That's
actually I think I'd have to dig into
their stack a little bit more to see how
meaningful that would be. I do know that
there's some talk of introducing a
similar kind of an aggregation method
into the ActivityPub world which believe
they're also calling a relay and to make
things even more complicated, Noster has
a concept of a relay. So, these three
different protocols using this term. I
think they're you know, you could do
essentially what a search engine does on
any of these things. You could go
crawling around for the data, pull them
into a fire hose and then tap into that
aggregation to produce bigger views of
the network. So, that principle can
certainly apply anywhere.
At protocol, I think it's a little bit
we focused on that from the get-go. We
focused really hard on making sure that
the data is signed at rest. That's why
it's called the authenticated transfer
protocol.
And that's a nice advantage to have when
you're running a relay like this because
it means that you don't have to trust
the relay.
Like generally speaking, when I look at
results from Google, you know, I'm
trusting pretty well that they're
accurately reflecting what's on the
website, which is fine. That's not
actually a huge risk or anything. But
whenever you're trying to build entire
applications and you're using somebody
else's relay, you could really run into
things where they say like, "Oh, you
know what? Paul tweeted the other day,
you know, I hate dogs." They're like,
"No, I didn't." Yeah, that's that's a
lie, right? And you just sneak in little
lies like that over a while it becomes a
problem. So, having the signatures on
the data is pretty important, you know,
if you're going to be trying to get
people to cooperate. You got to manage
the trust model. I know that ActivityPub
does have mechanisms for signing
records. I don't know how deep they go.
If they could fully replace that
utility. And then Mastodon and
ActivityPub, they also use a different
identifier system that they're actually
taking a look at DIDs right now. I don't
know what's going to happen there. We're
totally on board to give any kind of
insight that we got working on them. But
at the moment they use, think it's
WebFinger based identifiers. You know,
they look like emails. So, you got host
names in there and those identifiers
were being used in the data records. So,
you don't get that continuous
identifier. They actually do have to do
that hey, I moved, update your record
sort of thing. And that causes it to I
mean, it works like decently well, but
not as well as it could. They got us to
the point where it moves your profile
over and you update all the folks that
were following you so they can update
their follow records. But your posts,
they're not coming, right? Because
that's too far into that mesh of
interlinking records. There's just no
chance. So, that's kind of the upper
limit on that. You know, it's a
different set of choices and trade-offs.
You're always kind of asking like, well,
you know, is that how important is the
migration? Does that work out? Anyway,
now I'm just kind of digging into
differences between the two here.
I'm trying to understand the difference
there. So, you were saying that with
ActivityPub, all of the instances need
to be notified that you changed your
identifier, but then all of the messages
that they had already received, they
don't point to the new identifier
somehow?
Yeah, you run into basically just the
practicalities of actual engineering
with that is what happens, right?
Because if you imagine you got a
multi-million user social network, they
got all their posts. Maybe user has like
let's say a thousand posts and 10,000
likes.
And that activity can range back three
years, let's say. They change their
identifier and now you need to change
the identifier of all those records. If
you're in a traditional system, that's
already a tall order. You're going back
and rewriting a ton of indexes. You're
rewriting a lot of primary. Anytime
somebody replied to you, they had these
links to your posts. They're now you got
to update the identifier on all of those
things. You could end up with a pretty
significant explosion of rewrites that
would have to occur. Now, that's tough
if you're in a centralized model. If
you're in a decentralized one, it's
pretty much impossible because you're
now when you notify all the other
servers like, "Hey, this changed." How
successful are all of them at actually
updating those pointers? It's a good
chance that things are going to fall out
of correctness. That's just a reality of
it. So, if you've got a mutable
identifier, you're in trouble for
migrations. So, the DID is meant to keep
it permanent, you know? And it ends up
being the kind of the anchoring point.
If you lose control of your DID, well,
that's it. Your account's done.
But, we took some pretty traditional
approaches to that where the signing
keys get managed by your hosting server
instead of like trying to This may seem
like really obvious, but if you're from
the decentralization community, we spend
a lot of time like with blockchains
like, "Hey, how do I have the users hold
on to their keys, you know?" And the
tooling on that is getting better for
what it's worth. We're starting to see a
lot better key pair management in like
Apple's ecosystem and Google's
ecosystem, but it's still on the range
of like, "Nah, people lose their keys,
you know?" So, having the servers manage
those is important. And then we have
ways of exporting paper keys so that you
could kind of adversarially migrate if
you wanted to. That was, you know, in
the early spec it was we wanted to make
sure that this portability idea works.
You can always migrate your accounts.
So, you can export a paper key that can
override. And that was how we figured
that out. Like, okay, yeah, we don't
have to have everything getting signed
by keys that are on the user's devices.
We just need these master backup keys
that can say, "You know what? I'm done
with that host. No matter what they say,
I'm overriding what they think." And
that's how we squared that one.
So, it seems like one of the big
differences with account migration is
that with ActivityPub, when you move to
another instance, you have to actually
change your identifier. And with the app
protocol, you're actually not allowed to
ever change that identifier. And maybe
what you're changing is just you have,
say, some kind of a lookup, like you
were saying you could use a domain name
to look that up, get a reference to your
decentralized identifier, but your
decentralized identifier, it can never
change.
It can't change, yeah. And it shouldn't
need to, you know what I mean? It's
really a total disaster kind of
situation if that happens. So, that it's
designed to make sure that doesn't
happen. In the applications, we use
these domain name handles to identify
folks, and you can change those anytime
you want. Because that's really just a
user-facing thing. You know, then in
practice, what you see pretty often is
that you may if you change hosts, we
give subdomains to folks, you know, cuz
like not everybody has their own domain.
A lot of people do, actually, to our
surprise. People actually kind of
enjoyed doing that. But, a lot of folks
have just used them paul.bsky.social
as their handle. And so, if you migrated
off of that, you probably lose that. So,
your handle's going to change. But,
you're not losing the followers and
stuff cuz the internal system isn't
using paul.bsky.social. It's using that
DID, and that DID stays the same.
Yeah, I thought that was interesting
about using the domain names because
when you like, you have a lot of users,
everybody's got their own subdomain, you
could have however many millions of
users. Does that become an issue at some
point?
It's a funny thing. I mean, like the
number of users, like that's not really
a problem cuz you run into the same kind
of name space crowding problem that any
service is going to have, right? Like,
if you just take the subdomain part of
it, like the name Paul, like that.
There's only You're only going to have
one paul.bsky.social. In terms of the
number of users, that part's fine, I
guess. It's fine as ever.
You Where it gets more interesting, of
course, is like
really kind of around the usability
questions. For one, it's it's not
exactly the prettiest to always have
that bsky.social in there.
If we had some kind of solution to that,
we would use it, but like the reality is
that, you know, we've committed to the
domain name approach. And some folks,
you know, they kind of like, "Ah, that's
a little bit ugly." And we're like,
"Yeah, it is."
That's life, I guess. The plus side,
though, is that you can actually use
like TLD domain names, like on
pfrase.com. And that starts to get more
fun. It can actually act as a pretty
good trust signal in certain scenarios.
For instance, well-known domain names,
like nytimes.com, strong authentication
right there. We don't even need a blue
check for it. Similarly, the .gov domain
name space is tightly regulated. So, you
actually get a really strong signal out
of that. Senator Wyden is a one of our
users. So, he's It's wyden.senate.gov.
And same thing, strong you know, strong
identity signal right there. So, that's
actually a really nice upside. So,
that's like positives, negatives. Then,
that trust signal only works so far. If
somebody were to make pfrase.net,
then that could be a bit confusing.
People may not be paying attention to
the .com versus .net. So, it's not I
don't want to give the impression that
we've solved blue checks. It's a
complicated and multifaceted situation.
But, it's got some juice, you know. It's
also kind of nice, too, cuz folks, you
know, a lot of folks that are doing
social, they've got other stuff that
they're trying to promote, you know?
Like, I'm pretty sure that nytimes would
love it if you went to their website.
And so, tying it to their
online presence so directly like that is
a really nice kind of feature of it and
tells like I think a good story about
what we're trying to do with an open
internet where yeah, everybody has their
space on the internet where they can do
whatever they want on that and then they
these social profiles, it's that
presence showing up in a shared space,
you know, it's it's all kind of part of
the same thing. That feels,
you know, like a nice kind of
thing to be chasing, you know. It also
kind of speaks well to the the the
naming worked out for us. We we chose
@protocol as a name, you know, we
backronymed our way into that one cuz it
was a yeah, @ symbol sort of thing, but
like it actually ended up really
reflecting the biggest part of it which
is that it's about putting people's
identities at the front, you know, kind
of promoting everybody from a
second-class identity that's underneath
Twitter or Facebook or something like
that up into nope, you're free standing.
You exist as a person independently,
which is what a lot of it's about.
Yeah, I think just in general not
necessarily just for Blue Sky if people
had more of an interest in getting their
own domain, that would be pretty cool if
if people could tie more of that to
something you you basically own, right?
I mean, I guess you're you're kind of
leasing it from ICANN or whatever, but
Sure.
Yeah, rather than everybody having a
@gmail, Outlook, or whatever, they they
could actually have something unique
that they they control more or less.
Yeah, and we we actually have a little
experimental service for registering
domain names that we haven't integrated
into the app yet because we just kind of
wanted to test it out and and kind of
see what that appetite is for folks to
register domain names. Way higher than
you'd think. We did that early on, you
know, it's it's funny when you're you're
coming from decentralization is like an
activist space, right? Like it's it's
group of people trying to change how
this tech works and sometimes you're
trying to parse between what might come
off as a fascination of technologists
compared to what people actually care
about and it varies, you know. The
domain name thing is to a surprising
degree folks really got into that.
We saw people picking that up almost
straight away, kind of more so than the
certainly we ever predicted. And I think
that's that's just cuz I guess it you
know, it speaks to something that people
really get about the internet at this
point. Which is great. We did a couple
of other things that are similar and we
we saw varying levels of adoption on
them. We had similar kinds of user
facing opening up of the system with
algorithms and with and with moderation.
And those have both been pretty
interesting in and of themselves. So,
with algorithms what we did was we set
that up so that anybody can create a new
feed algorithm. This is kind of one of
the big things that you run into
whenever you use the app. So, if you
wanted to create a new kind of for you
feed, you can set up a service somewhere
that's going to tap into that firehose,
right? And then all it needs to do is
serve a JSON endpoint that's just a list
of URLs. They're like, here's what
should be in that feed. And then the
Blue Sky app will pick that up and and
send that you know, hydrate in the
content of the posts and show that to
folks. And so there's I want to say
this is a bit of a misleading number and
I'll explain why, but I think there's
about 35,000
of these feeds that have been created.
Now, the reason it's a little misleading
is that I mean, not significantly, but
it's not everybody went sat down in
their IDE and wrote these things. You
essentially one of our users created
actually multiple of our users made
little platforms for building these
feeds, which is awesome. That's the kind
of thing you want to see cuz we haven't
gotten around to it. Our app still
doesn't give you a way to make these
things, but they did and so lots of you
know, there's it's cool like one one
person made a kind of a combinatorial
logic thing that's like visual, almost
like scratch, you know, it's like so if
it has this hashtag and includes these
users, not those users and you're kind
of arranging these blocks and that
constructs the feed and then publish it
on your profile and then folks can use
it, you know. So, that has been, you
know, I would say a fairly successful
except we had one group of hackers do
put in a real effort to make a
replacement for you feed like magic
algorithmic feed kind of thing. And then
they kind of kept it going for a while
and then ended up giving up on it.
Most of what we see are actually kind of
weird niche use cases for feeds. You get
straightforward ones like content
oriented ones like a cat feed, politics
feed, things like that. It's great. Some
of those are using like ML detection. So
like the cat feed is ML detection. So
sometimes you get like a beaver in
there, but most of the time it's a cat.
And then we got some ones that are kind
of a funny like changing the dynamic of
freshness or selection criteria. Things
that you wouldn't normally see, but
because they can do whatever they want,
you know, they try it out. So like the
quiet posters ended up being a pretty
successful one. And that one just shows
people you're following that don't post
that often when they do, just those
folks. I use that one all the time
because yeah, like you lose track you
they get lost in the noise. So it's like
a way to keep up with them. The
moderation one, that one's a a real
interesting situation. What we did
there, essentially we wanted to make
sure that the moderation system was
capable of operating across different
apps so that they can share their work,
so to speak. And so we created what we
call labeling. And labeling is a
metadata layer that exists over the
network. Doesn't actually live in the
normal data repositories, it uses a
completely different synchronization
because a lot of these labels are
getting produced. It's one of those
things where the engineering
characteristics of the labels are just
too different from the rest of the
system. So we we created a separate
synchronization for this. And it's
really kind of straightforward. It's
here's a URL and here's a string saying
something like NSFW or gore or, you
know, whatever. And then those get
merged onto the records, brought down by
the client, and then the client, you
know, based on the user's preferences
will
put like warning screens up, hide it,
stuff like that. So yeah, these label
streams can then, you know, anybody
that's running a moderation service can,
you know, publish on these things, and
so anybody can subscribe to them, and
you get that kind of collaborative thing
we're always trying to do with this. And
we had some users set up moderation
services. So then as an end user you
find it it looks like a profile in the
app, and you subscribe to it, and you
configure it, and off you go. That one
has had probably the least amount of
adoption throughout all of them. It's a
you know, moderation is a sticky topic,
as you can imagine. Challenging for
folks. These moderation services, they
do receive reports, you know, like
whenever I'm reporting a post, I choose
from all my moderation services who I
want to report this to. What has ended
up happening more than being used to
actually filter out like subjective
stuff is more kind of like either
algorithmic systems or
what you might call
informational.
So, the algorithmic ones are like one of
the more popular ones is a thing that's
looking for posts from other social
networks, like this screenshot of Reddit
post or a Twitter post or a Facebook
post. Because
which you're kind of like why, you know?
But, the thing is some folks just get
really tired of seeing
screenshots from the other networks, cuz
often it's like look what this person
said. Can you believe it? You know, and
it's like
okay, I've had enough.
So, somebody made one of our users,
Andra, made a moderation service that
just runs an ML, detects it, labels it,
and then folks that are tired of it,
they subscribe to it, and they just
hide, you know? And so, it's like a
smart filter kind of thing that they're
doing. You know, hypothetically, you
could do that for things like spiders,
you know, like if you got arachnophobia,
things like that. So, that's like
pretty straightforward kind of automated
way of doing it, which takes a lot of
the spice, you know, out of out of
running moderation. So, that users have
been like, yeah, yeah, okay, we can do
that. Those are user-facing ways that we
tried to surface the decentralized
principle, right? And make take
advantage of how this whole architecture
can have this kind of a pluggability
into it. But then, really at the end of
the day, kind of the important core part
of it is those pieces we were talking
about before, the hosting, the relay,
and the the applications themselves,
having those be swappable in completely.
So, we tend to think of those as kind of
ranges of infrastructure into
application, and then into particular
client-side stuff. So, a lot of folks
right now, for instance, they're making
their own clients to the application,
and those clients are able to do
customizations, add features, things
like that, as you might expect. But,
most of them are not running their own
back end. They're just using our back
end. But, at any point, it's right there
for you. You know, you can go ahead and
clone that software and start running
the back end. If you wanted to run your
own relay, you could go ahead and go all
the way to that point, you know, if you
want to do your own hosting, you can go
ahead and do that. It's all there. It's
really just kind of a how much effort
your project really wants to take.
That's the kind of systemically
important part. That's the part that
makes sure that overall mission of
de-monopolizing
social media online, that's where that
really gets enforced.
And so, if someone has their own
data repository with their own users and
their own relay,
they can request that your relay collect
the information from their own data
repositories.
That's how these connections get made.
Yeah, and we have a fair number of those
already. Fair number of We call those
the self-hosters, right? And we got
I want to say 75 self-hosters going
right now, which is, you know, love to
see that be more, but it's really the
folks that if you're running a service,
you probably would end up doing that.
But, the folks that are just doing it
for themselves, it's the nerdiest of the
nerds over there doing that cuz it
doesn't end up showing itself in the in
the application at all, right? It's
totally abstracted away. So, that one's
really about like measure your paranoia
kind of thing. Or, if you're just proud
of the self-hosting or or curious, you
know, that's kind of where that sits at
the moment.
We haven't really touched on the fact
that there's this underlying protocol,
and everything we've been discussing has
been centered around the Blue Sky social
network, where you run your own instance
of the relay and the data repositories
with the purpose of talking to Blue Sky.
But, the protocol itself is also
intended to be used for other uses,
right?
Yeah, it's generic. The data types are
set up in a way that anybody can build
new data types in the system. There's a
couple that have already begun. Front
page, which is kind of a Hacker News
clone. There's Smoke Signals, which is a
events app. There's Blue Cast, which is
like a Twitter Spaces Clubhouse kind of
thing. Those are the folks that are kind
of willing to trudge into the the
bleeding edge and and deal with some of
the rough edges there. Pretty, I think,
obvious reasons a lot of our work gets
focused on making sure that the Blue Sky
app and that use case is working
correctly. But we are starting to round
the corner on getting to a full kind of
how to make alternative applications
state. If you go to the atproto.com,
there's a kind of a introductory
tutorial where that actually shows that
whole stack and how it's done. So it's
getting pretty close. There's a couple
of still things that we want to finish
up. We're we're working, for instance,
right now on OAuth for sign-in, which
we'll include with it better
permissioning, you know, which is very
important. What what kind of data does
the app get access to, make sure that's
getting enforced. But it'll be nice cuz
then when you're making one of these
apps, you get that kind of one SSO. You
press a button to sign in with whatever
and then that'll be nice. Yeah, so then
like the way that works roughly is you
set up a server and they'll SSO in and
then along with that session that's
being given to you, you get pointed to
like, okay, here's their account. Here's
the here's their DID, right? You use
that to look up their home server. And
then your app kind of
it's almost like you're being handed a
couple of databases to work with in a
way because their data repository is
their primary storage that you want to
write to. So what happens is they're
going to you're going to write your
normal server-side application. They're
going to ask like, "Hey, set my status
to blank or update my profile this way."
They'll send that request to your server
and then you're just going to send that
request over to their home server and
say like, "Okay, update this record for
me." And it'll say, "Great, done." And
then now it's committed to that kind of
primary storage. From there you've got
your view of the network that you've
accumulated that you've aggregated
together. You could go ahead and
optimistically update it and say like,
okay, I know that I just changed their
profile so that their display name
should change locally. But at the same
time what you're going to do is you're
going to listen to that firehose. And
eventually that right, you know,
hopefully pretty soon, that right you
just made will show up on that firehose
and then you ingest it in that way too.
And this is how you continue to be a
part of the larger network. It's not
just your users that you're observing.
You're seeing all the all the activity
by listening to the firehose. So it's a
little slight slight modification from
how you normally make a web app, but not
as much as you might think for a whole
protocol like this. Really comes down to
like writing to that home server and
then listening to that firehose. That's
kind of the the thing that that comes
along with it. And once you get used to
that it's pretty straightforward and in
fact it's kind of nice cuz you're not
having to do that, you know, those are
you're getting handed essentially part
of your stack as a part of the network.
So it's it's kind of a it's an
interesting way to to do this. We're
shaping that up now and I don't know,
maybe 6 months it'll feel pretty good by
then. We should get all the rough edges
kind of combed down.
So in a way you can almost think of it
as having an eventually consistent data
store on the network, I suppose, where
you don't have to architect that part.
You can make a traditional web
application with a relational database
and the source of truth can actually be
wherever that data repository is stored
on the network.
Yeah, that's exactly it is an eventually
consistent system. That's exactly right.
The source of truth is their data repo.
And that relational database that you
might be using, it's I think the best
way to think about it is like secondary
indexes or computed indexes, right? They
reflect the source of truth and you can
structure that whatever makes it easy
for you. Which is lucky cuz that's where
most of your data work is happening, you
know, like updating a row in a database,
not that big a deal. That and that you
just send that off to
to the personal server.
Yeah, all the heavy lifting is happening
in your aggregation database. And so,
you can use whatever you want there. And
that that is fortunate. Keeps it from
being too much of a pain.
And built into the protocol itself, is
there cuz you mentioned signing in with
OAuth, for example, then would you be
able to restrict an app that signs in as
you to only be able to write to certain
things in the data store, that kind of
thing?
Yeah. Yeah.
All the data's typed. We have a kind of
a reverse DMS identifier for the data.
So, Blue Sky posts are
identified with a type of
app.bsky.feed.post.
We did reverse DNS to make sure you
don't confuse it with a, you know, a web
address. It's jarring. At first, you're
like, what is this Java? But, you you
get used to it pretty fast. So, you get
these Everything's gets well defined.
You have these well defined schemas. And
as a consequence, it started off as just
like, well, let's make sure that people
making apps have a way to predict what
everybody's doing. That's why we
introduced that schema and typing
system. In previous projects I'd worked
on like Secure Scuttlebutt, we went
entirely by convention, and that was a
nightmare because you just never knew
what other folks were doing. There was
no coordination system. So, we had this
kind of a hacker ethos like, ah, now
you'll figure it out. But, no, actually,
you started to run into situations where
you would make a schema change in your
application that seemed benign, but
turns out you just broke two other apps
cuz you just didn't even know what they
were doing. So, the schema system is to
really just help developers coordinate
with each other. At least that was the
initial impulse. We get to the
permissions story, and we realize, oh,
man, we are lucky we did this because
now we have a way to describe in these
schemas what the different kind of
record types are. And so, whenever you
do your OAuth sign-in, it'll be able to
say, write to your Blue Sky posts, you
know, read your smoke signals events,
things like that. That permissioning
definitely a core piece of what the
OAuth is introducing.
That's pretty cool because it's taking
care of a certain part of your design,
right? In terms of how am I going to
store my data, how am I going to manage
permissions? At least that part is taken
care of for you.
Yeah, this is getting kind of grandiose.
I don't tend to pose in these terms, but
it is almost like we're trying to have
an OS layer at a protocol level where,
you know, permissioning in the in the
storage, it's like having your own like
network-wide database or network-wide
file system. You know, these are the
kind of facilities you expect out of a
platform like an OS. And so, the hope
would be that this ends up being
actually quite a convenient introduction
into the internet protocols, the
internet stack so to speak, so that it's
getting that usage outside of just the
initial
social app like we're doing here. If it
doesn't end up working out that way, if
this ends up, you know, good for the
Twitter-style use case, the other one's
not so much, that's fine, too. You know,
that's that's our initial goal. But we
we wanted to make sure to build in a way
that like, yeah, there's evolve-ability
to it. Keeps it Make sure that you're
getting the kind of most utility you can
out of it.
Yeah, I can see some of the parallels to
some of the decentralized stuff that I
suppose people are still working on, but
more on the peer-to-peer side, where the
idea was that I can have a network host
this data. But in this case, it's a
network of maybe larger providers, where
they could host a bunch of people's data
versus just straight peer-to-peer where
everybody has to have a piece of it. And
it seems like your angle there was
really the scalability part.
It was the scalability part. And there's
great work happening in peer-to-peer.
There's a lot of advances on it that are
still happening. I think really the
limiter that you run into
is running queries against aggregations
of data. Because you can get the
network, you know, BitTorrent sort of
proved that you can do distributed,
open, horizontal scaling of hosting, you
know, that basic idea of, "Hey,
everybody's got a piece and you sync it
from all these different places. We know
you can do things like that. What
nobody's been able to really get into a
good place is running queries across
large data sets in the model like that.
There's been some research in what is
what's called federated queries, which
is where you're sending a query to
multiple different nodes and asking them
to fulfill as much of it as they can and
then collating the results back, but it
didn't work that well. That's still kind
of an open question and until that is at
a place where it can like reliably work
and at very large scales, you're just
going to need a big database somewhere
that does give
the properties that you need. You need
these big indexes and once we were
pretty sure of that requirement, then
from there you start asking what about
the else about the system could we make
easier if we just apply some more
traditional techniques and merge that in
with the peer-to-peer your ideas. And
so, key hosting, that's an obvious one,
you know, availability, let's just have
a server, you know, it's no big deal.
But you're trying to you're trying to
make as much of them dumb as possible so
that they have that kind of easy
replaceability.
Earlier, you were talking a a little bit
about the moderation tools that people
could build themselves. There was some
process where people could label posts
and then build their own software to
determine what a feed should show per
person. But I think before that layer
for the platform itself,
there's a base level of moderation that
has to happen and I wonder if you could
speak to as the app has grown, how
that's handled.
Yeah, you got to take some
requirements in moderation pretty
seriously to start and with
decentralization, it sometimes that gets
a little bit dropped. You need to have
systems that can deal with questions
about CSAM, you know.
So, you got those big questions you got
to answer. And then you got stuff that's
more in the line of like, all right,
what makes a good platform? What kind of
guarantees are we trying to give there?
So, just not legal concerns, but, you
know, good product experience concerns.
That's something more in the realm of
like spam and and abusive behavior and
things like that. And then you get into
even more fine-grained like what is a
person's subjective preference and how
can they kind of make their thing
better? And so, you get a kind of
telescoping level of concerns from the
really big, the legal sort of concerns,
and then the really small subjective
preference kind of concerns. That
actually that telescoping maps really
closely to the design of the system as
well. Where the further you get up in
the kind of the legal concern territory,
you're now in court infrastructure. And
then you go from infrastructure, which
is the relay,
down into the application, which is kind
of a platform, and then down into the
client, and that's where we're having
those labelers apply. And each of them,
as you kind of move closer to
infrastructure, the importance of the
decision gets bigger, too. So, you're
trying to do just legal concerns with
the relay, right? Stuff that you
objectively can Everybody's in agreement
like, yeah, yeah, yeah. You know, no
bigs, don't include that. And the reason
is that at the relay level, you're
Anybody that's using your relay, they
depend on the decisions you're making,
that source selection you're doing, any
filtering you're doing. They don't get a
choice after that. So, you want to try
to keep that focus really on legal
concerns and doing that well, so that
applications that are downstream of it
can can make their choices. The
applications themselves,
you know,
somebody can run a parallel, I guess you
could call it like a parallel platform.
So, we got Blue Sky doing the
microblogging use case. Other people can
make an application doing the
microblogging use case. There's choice
that users can easily switch easily
enough switch between. It's still a big
choice. We're operating that in many
ways like any other app nowadays might
do it. You've got policies, you know,
for what's acceptable on the network.
You're still trying to keep that to be
as, you know, objective as possible,
make it fair, things like that. You want
folks to trust your T&S team. But from
the kind of systemic decentralization
question,
you get to be a little bit more
opinionated down all the way into the
client with that labeling system where
you can, you know, this is
individuals turning on and off
preferences. You can be as opinionated
as you want on that layer. And that's
how we have
basically approached this. And in a lot
of ways, it really just comes down to
in the day-to-day, the volume of
moderation tasks is huge.
You don't actually have high like stakes
moderation decisions most of the time.
Most of them are, uh, pretty
straightforward. Shouldn't have done
that. That's got to go. You get a couple
every once in a while that are a little
spicier or a policy that's a little
spicier. And it probably feels pretty
common to end users, but that just
speaks to how the volume of reports and
problems that come through. And
we don't want to make it so that the
system is seized up trying to
decentralize itself. You know, it needs
to be able to operate day-to-day. What
you want to make is, you know, back
pressure, you know, checks on that
power. So that if an application or
platform does really start to go down
the wrong direction on moderation, then
people can have this credible exit, this
way of saying, "You know what? That's a
problem. We're moving from here." And
somebody else can come in with different
policies better fit people's
expectations about what should be done
at these levels. So, it's not about
taking away authority, it's about
checking authority, you know, kind of
checks and balances mentality.
And high-level, cuz you're saying how
there's such a high volume of of things
that if you know what it is, you know
you want want it, but there's just so
much of it. So, is there Do you have
automated tools to label these things?
Do you have a team of moderators? Do
they have to understand all the
different languages that are coming
through your network? That that kind of
thing.
Yes. Yes. Yes, and yes.
Yeah, there's You use every tool at your
disposal to stay on top of it. Cuz, you
know, you you're trying to move as fast
as you can. Folks problems showing up,
you know, the slower you are to respond
to it the more irritating it is to
folks. Likewise, if you make a a missed
call if you somebody misunderstands
what's happening, which believe me is
sometimes just figuring out what the
heck is going on is hard. People's beefs
definitely surface up to the moderation.
Or, you know, misunderstanding or or
wrong application. You know, moderators
make mistakes, you know. So, you try to
maintain a pretty quick turnaround on
this stuff. And that's tough. And you
especially want to move fast on some
really upsetting content that can make
its way through. Again, illegal stuff
for instance, but war videos, stuff like
that, you know, it's real problem. So,
yeah, you're got to be using some
automated systems as well. Clamping down
on
bot rings and spam, you know, you can
imagine that's gotten a lot harder
thanks to LLMs, you know, like just
doing like uh text analysis by kind of
dumb statistics of what they're talking
about. That doesn't even work anymore
cuz the the LLMs are capable of
producing consistently varied responses
while still achieving the same goal of
like plugging a, you know, online
betting site of some kind, you know. So,
we do use kind of dumb heuristic systems
for when it works, but boy, that doesn't
work. That won't work for much longer.
And we've already got cases where it's
Oh boy, you know. So, that's
the moderation's in a dynamic place, to
say the least, right now with with LLMs
coming in.
It was tough before, now it's now it's
real interesting. So, you use everything
you can, and you keep playing a cat and
mouse game. That's that.
Are the the tools that you use, were
they all built in-house, or are there
Not all of them. We do
use a couple of services that are out
there. For one, with the C sand stuff,
there's a
company called Thorn that is actually
set up to handle that. Obviously, it's a
very sensitive kind of thing. They
maintain these hash fingerprint
databases that you we check in every
post, you know, hey, is this on your
database? We also use service called
Hive to help us automatically detect
pornography and gore. We're still tuning
that one, but
it hits significantly. It's correct more
than it's incorrect. And we we try to
have we encourage users to self-label
their stuff cuz, you know, nobody in my
good actors don't want to be posting
NSFW to people that don't want to get
it. We do see people do it, but we still
need to have that extra check. And so,
we're we're running the that kind of
detection on it and things like that.
And then we got a couple of in- house
things, something called AutoMod, uh
which you can find the source for.
That's just sitting there, and it's a go
data go code base that's sitting there
and running all kinds of heuristics,
trying to detect kinds of patterns of
behavior that we've identified as been a
problem. Often, that has to do with
spam. And then there's people.
Do you have a sense of
after you've gone through all these
tools, how many reports do people
actually have to flag a day or or
judge each day, I guess?
I don't have the numbers in front of me,
but our director of TNS is trying to
keep up with regular reports on that.
Uh so, I think actually, if you looked
up his account, he may have said
something about it recently. I just
don't have the numbers on me right
Yeah, cuz I think with any application
that has user-generated content, it just
seems like such a huge
challenge to deal with.
Yeah.
It is.
It really is. You know, it it shows up
in a lot of places. What's funny is what
we're talking about is the obvious way
that it shows up and even that is it's
not really apparent to the average
person just how much that really is.
It's a
pretty big task, but it also makes its
way into product development and is that
one of those hidden costs that shows up
all over the place. What it was funny
there's that meme about oh, I could
build Twitter in a weekend kind of
thing.
Right.
There's a lot of reasons why building a
a microblogging app had a lot of time to
reflect on how many weekends it was
taking to build it, you know.
And why it took longer than a weekend
for us.
Certainly targeting a lot of different
platforms will do it to you. The React
Native makes that a lot easier these
days and I'll give them a plug. They've
been great. The moderation, the safety,
that that part of the design that you
got to work into all new features, that
is a real hidden cost of product
development that you got to take
seriously from the get-go and you got to
look at every everything you do and say
what how's this going to get messed
with? What are people going to do with
this? And our track record's been pretty
good. There definitely moments where we
get something out and go ah,
you know, didn't think of that. That's
just how it goes, but that's
shows up everywhere.
For sure. Yeah. I didn't even think
about the fact where you had mentioned
the LLMs where
Oh, yeah.
now people just have the power to
generate posts that are
indistinguishable from people. So, I
don't know where we're going here, but
Somewhere new.
Yeah.
Any closing thoughts or other things you
want to mention?
Yeah, this has been an interesting
project. I'm happy with
how it's gone so far. For sure, the
first question that we had when we
started out was just whether or not it
would scale because historically folks
that work in the decentralization space,
that's what jams us up pretty bad. In
obvious ways for peer-to-peer, but even
blockchains actually got jammed up real
bad on scaling and that's that's kind of
why the NFT bubble popped as hard as it
did when it did was it's everybody knows
the transaction fees got really high.
It's because the system got too crowded.
And so, making these
big scale systems that have open
operation is a real challenge. And
that's the part that so far we're up to
now 11 million registered accounts and
we sit at somewhere around 1.5 to 2
million DAU.
And we haven't identified anything that
makes us think, "Ah, that's a scaling
limit for this design." We're pretty
sure that it can make its way all the
way to the kind of scale that people
expect out of this. So, I'm really happy
to see just kind of from the engineering
side of things like getting that
validated has felt pretty good about
this project. So, I'm I'm pretty curious
to see kind of how this all unfolds
moving forward. I'm feeling feeling very
happy with the outcome so far and just
actually genuinely interested on a
personal level to see how how these
dynamics play out over time. Really
looking forward to seeing somebody else
start to operate full nodes like we are.
I think that'll be a great milestone
that we're trying to head for. And
hopefully in a year or two, I think kind
of need to
make a little social network in a box,
make it a little bit easier for somebody
to just press a button and get the whole
thing going. That's a milestone in the
future I'm looking forward to. Other
than that, a lot of my day-to-day just
comes down to a lot of it's just running
the social app and learning all the
lessons that come along with that, which
has been a trip in and of itself.
Like you were mentioning, people think,
"Oh, build Twitter in a weekend." Right?
But it's taken a few more weekends than
that.
Taken a few more Your your problems only
just start.
You know, the all the source code is
available on GitHub. So, if you want to
see how we do it, it's right there. And
if you're an application developer, I
think in particular the social app repo
is pretty interesting to look at. That's
a a React Native repository. You can
kind of see the full thing. Lots of lots
of good forkable code in there if you're
building an app. So, we'll check that
out. All the protocol code is up there.
We got specs up on that protocol
website, so app.proto.com, you can check
all that out. Some good intro material,
things like that. You want to learn a
little bit more about how all this
works, but then on app.proto.com, it's
all up there. It's all ready to ready to
look at.
And if people want to follow you or see
what you're up to,
you're going to jump on Blue Sky and I'm
P Frazee dot com.
Paul, thank you so much for for taking
the time.
Absolutely, thank you.
This has been Jeremy Jung for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.